<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A petition apologeticall, presented to the Kinges most excellent Maiesty, by the lay Catholikes of England, in Iuly last</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1373:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A petition apologeticall, presented to the Kinges most excellent Maiesty, by the lay Catholikes of England, in Iuly last</title>
                  <author>Lecey, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Mogar, at the signe of the Compas [i.e. by the English secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Doway [i.e. England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: Io. Lecey.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; in fact printed in England by the secret press.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An apology or petition, of the lay-Catholikes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21675:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A PETITION</hi> APOLOGETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL, PRESENTED TO THE <hi>KINGES MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY,</hi> BY THE LAY CATHOLIKES OF ENGLAND, in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>In eo quod detractant de vobis tanquam de malefactoribus, ex bonis operibus vos conſiderantes, glorificent Deum in die viſitationis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that vvherein they miſreporte of you, as of malefactors, by the good vvorkes conſidering you, they may glorifie God in the day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</p>
               <bibl>1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at</hi> DOWAY <hi>by</hi> IOHN MOGAR, <hi>at the ſigne of the Compas.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21675:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21675:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVEREND SIR.</hi> There came to my hands by the way of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> on the <hi>xxviij.</hi> day of this moneth, a certayne <hi>Petition</hi> or <hi>Apologie of the lay Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes of England</hi> (as I ſtand informed) preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Highnes about the later end of the parliament: which ſeemeth ſo conformable to reaſon, ſo abſolute in forme of their ſubmiſsion, and ſo admirable for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance by them offered for their Prieſts and Paſtors: that the publiſhing thereof cannot but giue contentment (in my opinion) to all ſorts of men, that deſire both to be clearely informed of the true ſtate of things, and that iuſtice and equity ſhould take place, according to mens comportments &amp; deſerts, and not according to the preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate opinions of ſuch, whome nothing but the bloud and vtter beggering of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> can ſatisfie. And therefore I thought good, in more publike manner then it was before, to make the world acquainted therewith.</p>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>Reaſons of publiſhing this treatiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> publiſhing of this <hi>Apology</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but t<note place="margin">His Maieſties honour and ſeruice.</note>end much to his Maieſties honour, and more to his ſatisfaction and ſecuritie; for ſo much as the <hi>Catholikes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate ſeruices and obligations therein contayned, muſt needes be argumentes of ſome ſupereminent vertue and goodnes in his ſacred perſonage, that could drawe from them at all times ſuch extraordinary effectes of loue and deuotion: and the more manifeſt the proteſtations of their purgations ſhall appeare to the world, the more manifold ſhall be their bonds and obligations of performaunce, and perſeuerance therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prelates.</note>The <hi>Proteſtant Prelates</hi> cannot with reaſon diſalowe thereof, becauſe herein is nothing required at their hands, but a reaſonable conference, and ſatisfaction in pointes of their miſſion and vocation: And when they ſhall make it euident out of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21675:3"/>
written word, that they are the true Sheepheardes and Paſtors ſent from God to haue charge of ſoules, they make profer without delay to followe them, and with all confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to obey them, and heare their voyces: which when they ſhall proue, the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie is charitably compoſed, and though they fayle of their proofes, yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne as they doe with their wealth, their wyues, their pleaſures, and pallaces: the poore <hi>Catholikes</hi> deſiring only a ſecret and ſilent permiſsion of ſuch Paſtors, as ſhall ſhewe to them and the whole world, ſufficient euidence and approbation for the charge of ſoules they vndertake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Puritans</note>The <hi>Puritans</hi> herewith cannot be offended, if they peaceably, and preciſely ſeeke after contentment, and not contention: becauſe they ſhall finde diuers of their max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes zealouſly, or rather odiouſly conceiued by them againſt <hi>Catholikes,</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne and euacuated by moſt euident demonſtration and inſtances in matters of facte, practiſe and experience: eſpecially in that point of conditionall ſubiects, which is ſo much vrged by the <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Academikes of Oxford &amp; Cambridge.</note>The flouriſhing and learned <hi>Academikes</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> may perceiue hereby that <hi>Catholikes</hi> knowe their Prieſts <hi>intus &amp; incute,</hi> and take them neither for ignorant in diuinitie, nor dunces in humanity; neither for <hi>Catalines</hi> towardes their <hi>Senate,</hi> nor for <hi>Abſolons</hi> towardes their <hi>Dauid,</hi> that dare ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture life, &amp; liuing for their vertues &amp; loyalties. And I imagine that if your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> were put to the like plunges, they would hardly finde the like pledges: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could wiſh that your <hi>Miniſters</hi> would endeuour rather to excell and ſurpaſſe them in their Godly qualities, then in their pamphlets and pulpets to vrge the State to ſuppreſſe them with ſeuere exilementes and edictes, which are nothing but argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of their feare, and whetſtones of the others fortitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Artiſans, and Prentiſes.</note>The Godly and zealous <hi>Artiſans</hi> and <hi>Prentiſes</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and other places, may learne hereby to moderate themſelues a little in their outragious alarmes of <hi>Stoppe the Traytor,</hi> when they ſee an Innocent Prieſt paſſe their ſtreets: for by reading hereof they may be rightly and truly informed and inſtructed, howe farre the poore <hi>Innocent</hi> men are from treaſons, and all treaſonable purpoſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>The <hi>Catholikes</hi> at home muſt needes hereby be comforted, and animated in well doing, and faithfull ſeruing, and obeying their Soueraigne <hi>in pace &amp; gaudio,</hi> if they may be permitted; and if not that, yet in ſuffering with alacrity what ſhall be impoſed vpon them for their Religion, when by this <hi>Apologie</hi> they ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdned of thoſe former clogges and imputatims of diſloyaltie, and treaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes abroade.</note>The <hi>Catholikes</hi> not onely here in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> but in the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world beſides muſt needes be hereby much edified, and excited to the ſincere pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and profeſsion of zeale and pietie towardes God: of fidelity and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their Princes: and of a Reuerent respect, and regard towardes their Prieſts and Paſtors, when they finde in this preſent <hi>Apologie,</hi> ſo rare and remarkeable an example of <hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi> constancy in the one, &amp; conformity in the other:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21675:3"/>
and ſuch confidence for the third, that ſithence the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, and the dayes of the priuatiue Church of <hi>England,</hi> neuer the like Preſident, either in the time of peace, or perſecution hath beene heard or read of; that the ſheepe ſhould engage them ſelues for their ſhepheardes, and make voluntary profer to bee bound body for body, and life for life for their fidelity, except that famous <hi>Protomartir</hi> of <hi>England, S. Albane,</hi> who was to them herein a patrone and preſident: the end of whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conuerſation, our <hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi> beholding, doe Imitate his faith and fortitude, and doe ſucceed him in a reuerenciall but and deuotion towardes their Paſtors. Which heroicall minde and reſolution of our ſaid <hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi> muſt needes be as famous to poſterity, as it is repugnant to all worldly wiſdome and policy; and muſt alſo needes bee accompanied with aſmuch honour and merit in the ſight of God, and all good men; as it cannot but be incombred with dangers and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties in the ſight of fleſh and bloud, and of all thoſe <hi>quorum Deus venter eſt,</hi> Whoſe God is only their belly, profit, and pleaſure in this world.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Apologie</hi> two copies were ſent ouer, the one to <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the other to <hi>Flaunders:</hi> all one in ſence and ſubſtance, but it ſeemeth that the copie ſent to <hi>Flaunders</hi> was taken <hi>verbatim</hi> out of the firſt fountayne and originall: And that the other which came to <hi>Paris,</hi> was not all togeather ſo ample and compleate. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue thought good to aduertiſe you, that I haue followed and ſetforth that copie, which I found, or at leaſt preſumed to be moſt conſonant to the good mindes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of them, whome it moſt concerned.</p>
               <p>And thus willing you to make your profit ſpirituall of theſe my endeuours, and of the ſequent <hi>Apology,</hi> deſiring God that it may ſerue to mollifie the harts of our heauy aduerſaries, and fortifie and corroborate the Saints &amp; ſeruants of God in well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and patiently ſuffering, and carrying the Croſſe of Chriſt, &amp; Crowne of thornes which pricke to the quicke on euery ſide, I wiſh you the two moſt pretious Iewels that can happen to a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gratiam in hac vita, &amp; gloriam in futura.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From my study in <hi>DOWAY,</hi> 
                     <date>this <hi>16.</hi> of <hi>OCTOBER 1604.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your very louing Sonne and ſeruant in CHRISTO DOMINO. <hi>IO. LECEY.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:21675:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21675:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A PETITION</hi> APOLOGETICALL, PRESENTED TO THE KINGES <hi>MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE,</hi> BY THE LAY CATHOLIKES OF ENGLAND, in Iuly laſt.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 1.</hi> The cauſe of our ſilence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST MIGHTY AND GRATIOVS SOVERAIGNE. Many are the reaſons that haue cauſed vs to expect with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall patience, and profound ſilence, your <hi>Maiesties</hi> moſt gratious reſolution for ſome benigne remedy, and redreſſe of our moſt grieuous calamities and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: as the confidence of a good cauſe: the teſtemony of an incorrupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: the memory of our conſtant, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall affection to the vndoubted right &amp; Title, in remaynder of your renowned <hi>Catholike Mother,</hi> to the Crowne of <hi>England:</hi> the imputations, Croſſes, &amp; afflictions we ſuffred many yeares therefore: the publique and gratefull acknowledgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that your ſaid glorious <hi>Mother</hi> made thereof, at the time of her Arraynement and execution, in the preſence of the Lordes there aſſembled for her conuiction, vttering theſe wordes:<note n="*" place="margin">Her bloud is ſhed, &amp; yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth peace &amp; authority to vvorke them redemption of her ſo deſired.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe is me for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oore</hi> Catholikes, <hi>and the miſeries I foreſee they are like to endure for their irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable affection to me and mine; If I were as free as mine eſtate and innocency requireth, I would gladly redeeme their vexations with my deareſt bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame zeale &amp; promptitude after her deceaſe, we ſhewed in your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21675:5"/>
                  <hi>Maieſties</hi> right and pretention to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> the oppoſitions were made by vs and our <hi>Catholike</hi> brethren and freinds abroade and at home, leauing nothing in our power vndone, that might lawfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce your <hi>Maieſties</hi> rightful Title, as Heire apparant to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> againſt all practiſes or projects to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">The L Mont eagle, M Fran. Treſham, Sir Levvys Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, in the Tovvre of London.</note> Our forewardnes in proclayming your <hi>Maieſty</hi> without any further warrant then the right, and juſtice of your Title, and the loyaltie and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our hartes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Sir Thomas Treſham at Northampton</note>The dangers and difficulties that ſome amongeſt vs paſſed in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming thereof in times ſo greene and doubtfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">The Vicount Montiguelarg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly caſting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney among the people.</note> The general joy &amp; applauſe ſhewed by vs, with remarkable ſignes of infinite contentment at your Highnes entrance into the Realme, with dutifull offices of joy and readines to proclayme and receiue your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty,</hi> were performed by <hi>Catholikes,</hi> with ſuch alacrity in moſt places of the Realme, and thoſe in ſuch<note n="d" place="margin">The L. Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, The L. Mordent.</note> diſtance one from the other, that they could haue no intelligence one with another, howe they ſhould behaue them ſelues in that occaſion: which maketh it euident, that ſo generall a conſent, in ſo ſuddayne &amp; important an affaire, of perſons ſo by places deuided, could not proceede from any other fountayne, but from an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall and ſetled deuotion to your <hi>Maiesties</hi> vndoubted Title.</p>
               <p>All which offices of our loue and loyaltie, we aſſure our ſelues, are aſwell knowne to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> as your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Candor &amp; Clemency is knowne vnto vs, &amp; by vs blazed throughout the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world: And not by our tongues and pennes only are theſe your heroicall vertues made ſo notorious, as they are by the often publique and gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes alſo, &amp; proteſtations, which your <hi>Maieſty</hi> (out of the infinite boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and magnanimity of your minde) hath made, aſwell to Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, as to priuate Men at home: aſwell before as after the <hi>Queenes</hi> death, aſwell before as after your entrance to the Realme; both in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, and in publique; both in Pallace, and Parliament, <hi>that you would haue no bloud for Religion, that you would haue no ſale money for conſcience contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God, that you would reuiewe the lawes made againſt</hi> Catholikes, <hi>and giue order for clearing of them by reaſon, in caſe they haue beene in times past farther, or more rigorouſly executed by the Iudges then the meaning of the lawe was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The intended performaunce of which your moſt gratious promiſes receiued a memorable commencement in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt paſt, ſome fewe dayes before your Royall Coronation, when by ſpeciall order of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, without anie ſute or motion of the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> certayne Recuſantes of the beſt quality and ability, out of diuers partes of the Realme, were ſent for to <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> by the Lordes of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> priuy Councel,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21675:5"/>
and were by them very reſpectiuely and curteouſly vſed, and alſo aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſaid Lordes that your <hi>Maieſties Royall pleaſure and Clemency was to exonerate the</hi> Catholikes <hi>of this Realme from henceforth, of that pecuniary mulcte of</hi> xx <hi>pound a Moneth for recuſancy:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The xx pound a Moneth for Recuſancy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed by the K. voluntarie promiſe in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 1603.</note> which your <hi>Maieſties</hi> grace &amp; relaxation, the ſaid Lordes ſignified <hi>that they ſhould ſo long enioy, as they kept them ſelues vpright in all ciuill and true carryage towardes your</hi> Majeſty <hi>and the State, without contempt:</hi> whereunto reply was made, <hi>that recuſancy might be held for an acte of contempt:</hi> It was anſwered by the Lordes of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, <hi>that your</hi> Majeſty <hi>would not accompt recuſancy for a contempt:</hi> And this your <hi>Maieſties</hi> gratious order and pleaſure, the ſaid Gentlemen recuſants, were willed to ſignifie to all other <hi>Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which grace proceeding from your <hi>Maieſties</hi> meere Clemency and voluntary good will, in that moſt dangerous time of the diſcouery of the conſpiracy of the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> and <hi>Cobham,</hi> ſeemed to vs ſo inuiolable and ſo little ſubject to chaunge or alteration, that comparing theſe bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects with the repoſe and truſt, which your <hi>Maiesty</hi> (in your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted booke to your peereles Sonne) ſeemeth to put in them that were faithfull and reſolutely affected to your <hi>Mother,</hi> and with the ſpeach your Highnes made the firſt day of the Parliament tending to ſome more temperate courſe in matter of Religion then was of late vſed, we had great reaſon to abſtayne from farther importuning your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by friendes or petition, but to exſpect with ſilence, patience, and all humble ſubmiſſion, how your <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſhould pleaſe to diſpoſe of vs, without any diffidence or diſtruſt, either in our owne merits, or your mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 2.</hi> The Reaſons that haue driuen vs to breach of ſilence, and to a neceſſary and iuſt defence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT alas (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) we ſee our ſilence, modeſty, and ſimplicity ſo abuſed by ſome indiſcreete <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> who in their bookes and Sermons make it euident, that they thinke no abuſe or indignity offered vs, ſufficient to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their rigorous mindes, or ſuppreſſe our righteous cauſe, that we are driuen thereby to breake our determinate courſe of ſilence, vrged &amp; inforced thereto by theſe ſequent occaſions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that we ſee our ſelues, as ſuperſtitious perſons,<note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> excluded from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21675:6"/>
that ſupreame Court of Parliament, that was firſt founded by and for <hi>Catholike</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was furniſhed with <hi>Catholike</hi> Prelats, Peeres, &amp; Perſonages, and was indowed with thoſe goodly priuiledges &amp; prerogatiues by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> Princes, &amp; ſo continued from the firſt conuerſion of our Nation from <hi>Paganiſme</hi> for ſo many hundred yeares without alteration, till the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the vj. a Childe, and <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> a Woman: and by the lawes made by <hi>Catholikes</hi> in thoſe Parliaments, the honour, peace, and wealth of this Realme hath beene, and is maintayned, and your <hi>Maieſties</hi> right and ſucceſſion to the Crowne, mightly (againſt all your aduerſaries) fortified and ſupported.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 2. reaſon</note>We ſee daylie billes and bookes exhibited againſt vs in Parliament and elſe where, taxing vs very vnjuſtly with moſt odious names of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, ſectaries, ſuperſtitious perſons, and Idolators.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 3. reaſon.</note>We heare that your <hi>Maiesty</hi> is often ſollicited to extirpate the very roote, raſe, and memory of vs out of your Dominions, and rather to admitte Miſcreants and Iewes then <hi>Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 4. reaſon.</note>We heare a newe motion is made for the reuyuing of the former Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall lawes, and pecuniary payments, &amp; other penalties, rather charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs with a heauier hand, then eaſing vs of our former burdens: we heare that men are to pay for their Wiues recuſancy, which in the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and heauieſt times neuer was admitted: that the hauing or keeping of a Schoolmaſter (not allowed by the Dioceſan) is to be puniſhed with xl. ſhillings a day: that all ſuch as goe ouer to ſtudy in forraigne partes without ſpeciall licence, are to be diſabled of all Inheritaunce, Landes, Legacies, or other goodes, chattels or poſſeſſions whatſoeuer. Theſe inſtances duly conſidered, cauſe vs greatly to feare, that your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may in time, by the importunat and daylie clamors, and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations of our aduerſaries, be incenſed and incited againſt vs your moſt faithfull ſubjects, who liuing in certayne ſecurity of their owne inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and your <hi>Maieſties</hi> mercy and bounty, labour not by vnquiet oppoſitions to contradict the falſe informations of our aduers part, but only rely vpon the prouidence of God almighties protection, &amp; your <hi>Maieſties,</hi> who <hi>tanquam Pater patriae</hi> is and euer hath beene, the certayne ſanctuary, and common ſupport of all juſt and innocent men. And ſince the diſcharge of our minde, can in our poore opinion bring no other inconuenience, then light to your reſolutions, in ſuch thinges as your Highnes is now to determine of in this preſent Parliament, being the fitteſt time for your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to heare the deſires and requeſts of your people, and we hauing no other meanes to make them knowne, but by this our dutifull Petition, we are the boulder to preſent vnto your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21675:6"/>
viewe this our ſimple &amp; ſincere <hi>Apology:</hi> leaſt God ſhould be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with vs for our ſilence in matter of his honour: leaſt the <hi>Christian</hi> world ſhould condemne vs of negligence in defence of our poore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed cauſe: leaſt our Children and poſterity ſhould argue vs of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes and puſilanimity in a cauſe concerning their liues, eſtats, and their very ſoules ſaluation: finally leaſt our aduerſaries ſhould inſult ouer vs and repute vs <hi>tanquam confitentes reos,</hi> if after ſo many blowes giuen, we ſhould not hold vp the Buckler-hand to ſaue our heads from vtter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and deſtruction, and leaue ſome monument to our poſterity of our zeale and deuotion <hi>in negotio animarum,</hi> &amp; of our duty and affection, <hi>in cultu Principum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet ſo deſirous we are to giue your <hi>Maieſty</hi> all poſſible contentment and ſatisfaction, ſo loath not only to commit, but to conceaue any thing that might juſtly offend your Grace, that being by the reaſons aforeſaid preſſed to put penne to paper, and to haue recourſe to your Highnes by way of interceſſion, we ſeeke not for all that to importunate your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> with concourſe of multitudes, nor with the ſubſcriptions of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of your lay <hi>Catholike</hi> ſubjects handes<note n="a" place="margin">As the Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters lately did.</note> (as ſome others haue done, <hi>in alio genere</hi>) for the furtherance of their affaires: but ſome fewe of vs only in the name of the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of all degrees (who euery way joyne with vs in our ſubmiſſion and purgation) doe preſent this our ſincer <hi>Apology</hi> and humble Petition, wherein if we ſeeme more tedious forth: diuers important pointes wee muſt neceſſarily handle by this occaſion then is conuenient for men that deale with ſo mighty a <hi>Monarche,</hi> buſied ſo extreamely with the waighty affaires of ſo many Kingdomes: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>(O noble Prince)</hi> this our <hi>indecorum,</hi> for that we are driuen to touch ſomewhat in this diſcourſe, which in Parliament we ſhould haue ſaid, if we thether had bin admitted: that which to our aduerſary we would vtter, if they had the patience to heare vs: and that which we ſhould anſwere to their ſiniſter ſuggeſtions, if we might haue that acceſſe to your Royall perſon, as the extreamity of our cauſe requireth, and the true and hartie affection we beare to your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the common wealth of your Potent <hi>Monarchie</hi> deſerueth. It is not our meaning (moſt mighty <hi>Monarch</hi>) being meere lay men, that make no profeſſion of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, to examine curiouſly &amp; contentiouſly all that our aduerſaries haue thundred of late againſt vs, or to diſpute with them in moode &amp; figure, which combate we leaue to the diuines of both partes, when your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> ſhall thinke good thereof: but with due reſpect to giue your Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an account and reaſon of our beleef and Religion, and a full and ampl ſecuritie and ſatisfaction, of our fidelities and ſubmiſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21675:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 3.</hi> The Estate and quality of your Maieſties Catholikes ſubiects.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the cleare vnderſtanding of which two points, may it pleaſe your Grace to conſider; firſt what is the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of your faithfull &amp; <hi>Catholike</hi> ſubjects both for number, quality, and deſert; next what Religion it is they profeſſe, &amp; vpon what groundes; laſtly what they are of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſubjects of their Ranke, that for former or future ſeruices, and ſubmiſſion in all ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and temporall cauſes, againſt all both domeſticall and forraigne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, haue and will goe farther, or venter more willingly their liues &amp; liuings for the honour and defence of your perſon, greatnes, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, then they, and their friends both haue, and will doe.</p>
               <p>In deliuery of which points, we hope your <hi>Maieſty</hi> will expect no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arte, or eloquence then may be required of men plunged, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed with the flux and reflux of perpetuall vexations, which is truth that craueth juſtice, and teares that cry for mercy.</p>
               <p>It is euident (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) that the ſubjects of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Realmes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> conſiſt of <hi>Catholikes, Proteſtants, Puritans,</hi> and other ſectaries: the <hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Catholikely</hi> affected in this Realme, not withſtanding the long perſecutions in the late <hi>Queenes</hi> dayes, were at the entrance of your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to this Realme, eſteemed to be as many, as any other of the ſaid profeſſions of Religion: and as for <hi>Ireland</hi> few there are of that nation,<note place="margin">An Iriſhman a Proteſtant is cara auisin terris.</note> that are of any account or freehold, but are profeſſed <hi>Catholikes,</hi> beſides thoſe that are <hi>Catholikely</hi> affected.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of this Realme, it is well knowne that their Anceſtors haue deſerued well of this common wealth both in warre, &amp; peace, both at home and abroade, and for their fidelities, and laudable ſeruices haue bin aduanced by your <hi>Maieſties</hi> progenitors, vnder whome they liued and ſerued, from whome we hope that in no point we dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate; only that which in them was eſteemed the poleſtarre of all their vertues (to witte) the <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion, is in vs puniſhed for wickednes and impiety.</p>
               <p>This did our <hi>Catholike</hi> Parents, dignified by your <hi>Maieſties Catholike</hi> progenitors, leaue vs to ſucceede them in: their Religion towards God; their fidelity towards our Princes; &amp; their natiue freedome in this your Realme of <hi>England,</hi> which we haue loſt of late yeares vnder the Raigne of our late <hi>Queene,</hi> for no other crime or offence, then for that we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21675:7"/>
to ſerue God as our <hi>Catholike</hi> Forefathers haue done before vs, euer ſince the conuerſion of our Country from <hi>Paganiſme;</hi> &amp; to ſaue our ſoules, which are more pretious in his ſight, then all the Kingdomes in the world: and although we were debarred from all offices and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities, and liued as it were in perpetuall baniſhment and confinement: yet was it neuer heard that any one of our number of ſuch ſuffering re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, euer lifted vp a finger to the leaſt damage, or detriment in the world of our Prince or Country. And thus by theſe few lines your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> may ſee the multitudes condition, and diſpoſition of your <hi>Catholike</hi> ſubjects; who humbly proſtrate at your <hi>Maieſties</hi> feete, craue to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their former and ancient freedome.</p>
               <p>What we haue here ſpoken, or ſhall hereafter ſpeake of our hard vſage in our late <hi>Queenes</hi> dayes, we are driuen thereto by neceſſity, for mouing your <hi>Maieſty</hi> to commiſeration, by comparing in your wiſdome the grieuouſnes of our puniſhment, with the quality of our deſerts, that there vpon you may temper the aſperity of the former proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, which our late Soueraigne her ſelfe in her late dayes beganne to doe, giuing the world to vnderſtand by the laſt proclamation that euer ſhe made in that kinde, that ſhe beganne to diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon;</hi> and aſwell therein, as in diuers other bookes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations tending to that purpoſe, before publiſhed vpon any noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious execution done vpon <hi>Catholikes,</hi> ſhe diuers times, and by her Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſadors to diuers Princes abroad did promiſe and proteſt, that her will and intention was not to puniſh her ſubjects for their<note n="a" place="margin">Our late Queene euer made profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that ſhee meant neuer to puniſh for Religion.</note> Religion and conſcience, whereby we conceiued ſome hope, and found ſome effect a litle before her <hi>Maieſties</hi> death, and in this minde and diſpoſition God did take her, and your <hi>Maieſty</hi> found vs: which conſidered, we hope your <hi>Maieſty</hi> hauing no occaſion to hate vs, and we many old and newe occaſions to loue you, that you will rather imitate your predeceſſor in her firſt, beſt, and laſt diſpoſition tending to mildnes, mercy, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, then in her other hard and ſharpe courſes: ſithence the fruites and effects of the one, were<note n="b" place="margin">The fruites of a ſvveete &amp; milde courſe.</note> joy, peace, abundance, and vniuerſall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and combination of mindes &amp; affections, both at home &amp; abroad (which your <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſeemeth moſt to deſire) and the harbingers and handmaydes of the other, haue beene<note n="c" place="margin">The hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids of bloud &amp; perſecution.</note> warres, diſcenſions, diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, bloud, and beggery; (which your Grace cannot ſo well digeſt.) And that appeareth moſt euidently by the firſt twelue yeares of the late <hi>Queenes</hi> Raigne, which as they were free from bloud and perſecution, ſo were they frawght with all kinde of worldly proſperity; no Prince was for that ſpace better beloued at home, or more honoured or reſpected
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21675:8"/>
abroad, no ſubjects euer liued with greater ſecurity or contentment; neuer was the Realme more opulent or abundant; neuer was both in Court and Country ſuch a generall time of triumph, joy, and exultation: but no ſooner did ſhe beginne to alter her courſe, &amp; to enter into bloud, but all was filled with feares and ſuſpitions at home, with warres and diuiſions abroad, and with continuall fright and allarames of ſtrange at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, either againſt her perſon or ſtate: and in fine when her treaſure was exhauſted, her ſubjects &amp; Kingdomes extreamely impoueriſhed, and all the Kingdomes almoſt about vs diſguſted, and in open tearmes of jeloſie and hoſtilitie with her, ſhe beganne agayne to thinke of her former fortunate dayes, and to incline to a milder courſe, as the only meanes to ſettle her and her Realme in peace, ſecurity, and former proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity: which times compared together, doe demonſtrate that the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of lawes made againſt <hi>Catholike,</hi> were the forerunners of infinite miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes and miſeries. And leaſt your <hi>Maieſty</hi> beholding ſuch bloudy &amp; ſtrange laws made againſt vs, with their rigorous execution by the ſpace of ſo many yeares in ſo long a Raigne, as was that of our late <hi>Queene;</hi> might thereby conjecture that ſuch newe and neuer hard of decrees, could not without vrgent or notorious occaſions haue beene inuented, conſtituted, and ſo ſeuerely executed; leaſt this apprehenſion of theſe former proceedinges might make the like impreſſion in your minde, &amp; auerſion from vs; we humbly craue your <hi>Maieſties</hi> gratious eares and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: And when you ſhall reuiewe, and conſider deeply the lawes made againſt vs, and compare them with the objected crimes, that then ſome ouerture may be propoſed to the preſent Parliament for clearing the lawes by reaſon, which is the ſoule of the lawe to them, that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may be made by juſtice betweene the innocent and guilty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for howſoeuer the late<note n="a" place="margin">The reaſon that might moue the late Queene to make lavves againſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>likes.</note> 
                  <hi>Queene</hi> might haue pretention to make them, both by reaſon of her illegittimation by her owne Father in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Parliament notoriouſly diuulged, and the jelouſie ſhe euer ſtood in of the <hi>Queene</hi> your gratious <hi>Mother,</hi> both for the backe and alliaunce ſhe had with <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the right ſhe ſeemed to haue by the ſentence of the Church, pronounced againſt the diuorce of her Father; and the diuers cenſures and excommunications promulgated againſt her: Yet your <hi>Maieſty</hi> (of whoſe rightfull ſucceſſion &amp; moſt lawfull, and legitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat poſſeſſion of this Crowne, <hi>Satan</hi> himſelfe being put to his ſhifts can make no doubt or difficulty; againſt whome no Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petitor either hath, or had purpoſe, or powre to contend;<note n="b" place="margin">Vide D. Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Monſieur de Bethunes let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</note> whome the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo farre from cenſuring, that ſhe hath already cenſured all thoſe that ſhall any way ſeeke to giue you any diſturbaunce or moleſtation; &amp; with whome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21675:8"/>
all the Princes in <hi>Christendome</hi> are in perfect peace and amity; &amp; whome <hi>Catholikes</hi> haue as yet no way offended, but by all meanes indeuoured to ſerue, ſatisfie, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent.)<note n="a" place="margin">His Maieſtie hath no ſuch reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the lavves againſt Catholikes, as the late Q. had to inact them.</note> Your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> (we ſay) for theſe reſpects, hath no ſuch apparent cauſe to continue thoſe lawes, as the late <hi>Queene</hi> had to inact them, the reaſons and foundations of thoſe lawes, being by this happy mutation of ſtate, time, and perſons vtterly remoued.</p>
               <p>If then (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) we haue beene, are, and will be (as we haue and will demonſtrate) as loyall, faithfull, and affectionate to your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> your predeceſſors and poſterity, and euen to thoſe Princes that dealt moſt hardly with vs, and to the good and peaceable eſtate of our Country, as any ſorte of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſubjectes within the Realme of our Ranke whatſoeuer; we ſee not howe by authority we can be driuen to forſake our <hi>Catholike</hi> Fathers faith and beleefe, vnleſſe authority can by reaſon conuince vs, that our faith is Infidelity, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſuperſtition, and the ſeruice we vſe Idolatry, or the Doctrine we receiue hereſie. Theſe are points firſt to be decided and determined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Deuines and learned men of both partes; and therefore that Magiſtrates ſhould proceede againſt vs, as men conuicted of thoſe crimes, before our cauſe be heard and determined, by them that are by God appointed to handle thoſe high and important pointes of diuinity; we hope your <hi>Maieſties</hi> clemency and piety will not permitte: But judgment being paſt on our ſide already, in ſo many generall Councels abroade, and conuocations and Parliaments at home, commending and approuing the faith we profeſſe, what reaſon can giue life to that lawe, that doth reuerſe a ſentence ſo authentically giuen, without the full forme of juſtice and proceſſe therein required?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 4</hi> The reaſons why we are ſo reſolute in our Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſons of Religion.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt reaſon that we giue of our faith &amp; Religion (SACRED SOVERAIGNE) &amp; why we ought not to ſuffer therefore as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents is, that neither obſtinate pride, <note place="margin">The 1. reaſon.</note> nor preſumptious pertinacy, nor diſlike of order or Diſcipline, nor contempt of authority, nor curioſity, affectation of nouelty, or diſcontentment in our priuate humors maketh vs ſo conſtant and reſolute in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21675:9"/>
thereof: but our conſciences meerely ſo informed and inforced in manner, by the inſtinct of Gods grace, and reuelation of his holy word and will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but our vnderſtanding captiuated in <hi>obſequium fidei</hi> by moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident<note n="a" place="margin">In no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but the Catholike on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe all theſe Teſtemonies concurre.</note> Teſtimony of holy Write, of Vnity, Vniuerſality, Succeſſion, Antiquity, &amp; authority of Scriptures, Fathers, Saints, Doctors, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, Parliaments, Virgins, and Martirs, which all concurre only, and joyntly in the <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion, and in no other profeſſion whatſoeuer: which conſiderations accompayned with the feare of Gods judgments, the danger of Hell fire, and the deſire of eternall Saluation, commaund vs by the rules of reaſon, in the practiſe &amp; profeſſion of that Religion, to obey the lawe of God before the lawe of Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 2. reaſon.</note>It is an inſtance and maxime that ſuffereth no exception, that neuer any generall or vniuerſall innouation, or alteration in matters of Faith or Religion from badde to better, hath beene heard of, either in the whole world, or in any particular nation, be it either from <hi>Iudaiſme, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſme, Paganiſme, Atheiſme,</hi> or <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but that the commiſſion and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the meſſengers haue beene authoriſed <hi>Domino coöperante &amp; ſermonem confirmante ſequentibus ſignis:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> our Lord working with all, and confirming the word with ſignes that followed: which ſithence our new meſſengers and reformers, as yet, haue not duly, nor clearely ſhewed (pretending as they doe to purge <hi>Christendome</hi> of ſuperſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) howe can they in reaſon craue at our handes, credit, or conformity to the newe lawes made on that behalfe? God is <hi>ipſa vita, lux, &amp; veritas.</hi> God that is the life,<note place="margin">The 3. reaſon.</note> light, and truth it ſelfe cannot giue commiſſion, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and authority, to death, darknes, &amp; falſhood; but it is moſt euident and cannot be doubted of or denied, that the firſt Apoſtles &amp; Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this our nations of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland, Fraunce,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> were ſent from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deliuered vs the ſame <hi>Romane</hi> faith we nowe profeſſe; the ſame <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Sacraments;</hi> and preached the ſelfe ſame Doctrine,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Domino coöperante &amp; ſermonem confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mante ſequentibus ſignis:</hi> our Lord working with all, and confirming the word with ſignes that followed. Reaſon then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth thus, that either God in this caſe hath giuen teſtemony to falſhood, or elſe the doctrine confirmed by the teſtemony of God is true and auowable, and not to be forſaken for feare of any humane lawes, till we haue like teſtemony from Heauen to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary; &amp; when our aduerſaries ſhal duly reproue ours herein, and make their owne miſſion as manifeſt by the word of God, then if we doe not conforme our ſelues to the newe lawes impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon vs, worthely we are to endure theſe late inflicted penalties for matter of recuſancy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21675:9"/>To conuince vs then, that either we haue not the true Scriptures,<note place="margin">The 4. reaſon.</note> or interpret them not as we ought, or that we diſhonour God in honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Saintes, or erre in the number, or nature of our Sacraments, or that our Doctrine is falſe and defectiue, and to condemne vs, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs therefore as Heretikes and Idolators; requireth in all reaſon an abſolute commiſſion from God: the which when it ſhall be produced, willingly we will obey.</p>
               <p>If they alleadge Scriptures, the Scriptures are common to vs both,<note place="margin">The 5 reaſon.</note> yet more likely in reaſon to be ours then theirs; becauſe that if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had not conſerued them, and communicated the ſame vnto vs, our aduerſaries had beene at this day Scriptureleſſe: the very originall Bible, the ſelfe ſame <hi>numero</hi> which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſent in with our Apoſtle S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> being as yet reſerued by Gods eſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as a Teſtemony,<note n="a" place="margin">We receiued the Scriptures from the Church of Rome.</note> that what Scriptures we haue, we had them from <hi>Rome,</hi> and haue nothing of our reformers, but that we haue not ſo many bookes of Scriptures diſcanonized and rejected, becauſe they be expreſſe Teſtimonies againſt their newe and negatiue Religion.</p>
               <p>If they ſtand vpon the ſence and true interpretation, we ſtand on that point more confidently then they, they hauing no further warrant then their priuate ſpirit, and we relying on the aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt therein promiſed to his Church for the inſtruction of all truth; which is <hi>Columna &amp; firmamentum veritatis,</hi> the piller &amp; foundation of truth. If they ſlie to the Fathers, for one place euill vnderſtood &amp; ſome time falſified, ſome time mutilated, and ſome time wholy corrupted, we produce a thouſand, not by patches nor mammocke as they doe; but whole pages, whole chapters, whole bookes, and the vniforme conſent of all the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers and <hi>Catholike</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>If they preſſe vs with their paſſed Parliaments and Princes, for one of theirs we haue an hundred, and for a Child <hi>King,</hi> &amp; a Woman <hi>Queene,</hi> we haue for vs ſo many, ſo Holy, ſo Wiſe, ſo Learned, ſo Religious, ſo Victorious Princes, as our Hiſtories without them would be very bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, our Names obſcure, our Clergy miſerable, our Biſhops beggerly, our Parliaments confuſed, our Lawes intricated, our Vniuerſities with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Colledges, our Colledges without Schollers, our Schollers without maintenaunce. Reaſon then the life of the lawe, requireth to our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding more ample and authenticall euidence, before we be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by lawe, as ſuperſtitious or irreligious.</p>
               <p>The faith we profeſſe,<note place="margin">The 6. reaſon. Rom. cap. 1.</note> is that faith and Religion which S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſo highly commendeth, which therefore is called <hi>Catholike</hi> and <hi>Romane,</hi> becauſe<note n="b" place="margin">The Church of Rome euen vvas and is the Mother Church.</note> al the Churches in the world either did in their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21675:10"/>
or doe for the preſent agree vniformely with the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in vnion and communion of faith, doctrine, and fellowſhippe; hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereto as to the <hi>Mother</hi> Church. From the Paſtors and Prelates of this Church, to witte, from<note n="a" place="margin">S. Gregory the Pope S. Auguſtine the Monke</note> S. <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the <hi>Monke,</hi> we receiued the benefit of our conuerſion and regeneration; from them we receiued the ſelfe ſame Doctrine, Diſcipline, Seruice, Sacraments, Feaſts, and laudable Cermonies, which are by vs held, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized, profeſſed, and defended with the effuſion of our bloudes at this very day, and this we finde verified by the Hiſtories of<note n="b" place="margin">S. Bead, Cambden, Stovve, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſhed, and Sauel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Bead, Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Hollenſhed, Stowe,</hi> and that Tripartite Hiſtory ſet out by Maſter <hi>Sauell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 7. reaſon.</note>From this Church of <hi>Rome</hi> we receiued our Bible, our Goſpell, our Creede, our Cannons; which are the ſame through the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world among <hi>Catholikes,</hi> both for the tranſlation, ſence, and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 8. reaſon.</note>This Church is by your <hi>Maieſty</hi> and by the learned ſorte of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> acknowledged to be the <hi>Mother</hi> Church; wee hope then we are excuſable, that reuerence &amp; loue our deareſt <hi>Mother,</hi> from whoſe breaſt our forefathers and we haue receiued the ſweet milke of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 9. reaſon.</note>There was neuer yet ſince the Incarnation of Chriſt any hereſie that crept into the Church of God, but we finde the names of the authours of ſuch hereſies: we finde by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Councels called to condemne them, and Doctors imployed to confute them: there is not the leaſt Ceremony or circumſtance that hath beene added, for the greater Majeſty and ſolemnity in Gods deuine ſeruice, but the yeare is knowne when, and the <hi>Pope</hi> by whome it was ordayned.</p>
               <p>If matters then of ſo ſmale moment paſſe not without recording, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would that the lawes that muſt condemne our <hi>Mother</hi> Church of Idolatry and ſuperſtitions, ſhould tell vs the authours that firſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted her integrity: but if the firſt jnuentors and jnſtitutors of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> of prayer to <hi>Saintes,</hi> and the like ſuppoſed errors, cannot be produced, doubtleſſe we muſt attribute them, as wee doe indeede to Chriſt and his Apoſtles: and as deriued from ſuch infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible authority, we are bound in all equity to followe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 10. reaſon</note>But if by the fruits your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> will giue judgement of the tree, the fruites of our Religion are Loue, Vnity, Concord, Piety, actes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Deuotion: as Faſting, Prayer, Almes, building of Moneſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, erecting of Vniuerſities, founding of Hoſpitals, conuerting of Nations, calling of Councels, confuting of Hereſies, obedience to our Princes <hi>though they bee</hi> Pagans <hi>and</hi> Infidels, <hi>and that for conſcience ſake,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21675:10"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Calu. lib. 4. Inſt. cap. 4 lib. 4. cap. 10. 6. 5.</note> whereas both practiſers and profeſſors of the Religion which we are ſo preſſed to embrace, doe farre differ from vs in thoſe pointes, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vnder colour of the libertie of the Goſpell,<note n="b" place="margin">Knox in his exhortation to England prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Geneua. 1559.</note> contempt of power, and authoritie<note n="c" place="margin">Luther in his booke de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate ſeculari: &amp; in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the 1. of S. Peter, cap. 2.</note> neglect of lawes,<note n="d" place="margin">Goodman in his booke of obedience: all vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch teach contempt of authority, and neglect of lavves in the places cited.</note> and obedience. The examples are to late, and lamentable in your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in the Perſons of your gratious <hi>Mother,</hi> and <hi>Grand-Mother; Father,</hi> and <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> to paſſe with ſilence the tragedies by ſuch like, played in ſundrie other Countries. Reaſon then the life of the lawe will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite vs, if we preferre a Faith that hath taken ſo deepe roote, whoſe goodlie fruites wee daylie ſee and taſte, before a ſlender, ſleight, greene, and farre leſſe fruitfull plant.</p>
               <p>About twentie foure yeares nowe paſt, when a certaine conference was helde in the Tower betweene Maſter <hi>Campion,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Sherwin Catholike Prieſtes,</hi> and ſome of the ſelected learned <hi>Proteſtant</hi> diuines, there were then in priſon in the Fleete, diuers <hi>Catholikes</hi> both of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vvorſhippefull degree, for Teſtemony of their conſcience only; as the Lord <hi>Vaux,</hi> Maſter <hi>Thomas Somerſet</hi> brother to the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Threſham,</hi> Sir <hi>William Catſby,</hi> &amp; others: who offered the warden of the Fleet (to procure them licence of the priuy Councell, to be preſent at that conference, and to haue that queſtion of reparing to the <hi>Protestant</hi> Church diſcuſſed and decided) one hundred French Crownes for euery day that this queſtion ſhould remayne thus vnder examination: but their requeſt could not then be admitted, albeit the ſaid warden did vndertake the ſute, and confidently promiſed to effect it, and ſeriouſly laboured it aſwell by his honourable friendes in Court, as by all other meanes he could poſſibly.</p>
               <p>The ſame offer of conformity, and deſire to be ſatisfied in this point, which we made then, we in humble wiſe make nowe, and that with ſo much the more greater efficacy, as your <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath a moſt full and ample poſſeſſion of our hartes and affections, for manifold important reſpectes, both for the loue your gratious <hi>Mother</hi> did beare vs, and the cauſe for which we ſuffer: as alſo for the often (to vs moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable) proteſtations your <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath made, and that in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and in priuate, <hi>that you haue a minde free from perſecution, or thraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling your ſubiects in matters of conſcience; that you would not increaſe our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens with</hi> Roboam; to which adding your Clemency of which wee haue taſted, and your Gratious promiſes where vvith wee liue in hope, and your daylie diſcourſes ſpringing from your natiue boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and benignity; make vs ſtrayne our ſelues to the vttermoſt, to giue your Grace ſatisfaction. And therefore if we may obtayne this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21675:11"/>
fauour at your Graces handes, to be aſſured in conſcience, by the deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the learned Deuines of both ſides, that the act of going to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> ſermones and ſeruice, is not a damnable ſinne: then if after ſuch<note n="a" place="margin">A moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable requeſt A Councell, conference of diſputation.</note> diſpute, deciſion, &amp; information, we ſhall refuſe to conforme our ſelues to your <hi>Maieſties</hi> will and example, we thinke then there is reaſon to giue life and reeſtabliſhment to the lawes made againſt vs. And this may ſuffiſe (we hope) for diſcharge of the dutifull reſpect we beare to your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and deſire we haue to giue your Grace all poſſible ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in matter of our beleefe and Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 5.</hi> The proofes of the lay Catholike fidelities.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſons of loyaltie.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND nowe we come to the matter of our loyaltie &amp; obedience (GRATIOVS SOVERAIGNE) in the defence whereof we are driuen by the neceſſity of our affaires; and importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our oppugners, to inſiſt more particulerly, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were conuenient in reſpect of our owne modeſty, or your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bounty and magnanimity; who neuer yet omitted to recompence and pay, <hi>ſuo loco &amp; tempore,</hi> loue with loue, ſubjection with protection, and vertue with honour.</p>
               <p>For the full &amp; finall clearing therefore of that point of diſobedience, and diſloyalty, wherewith wee are ſo often charged rather in hatred of Religion, then of any ground or ſubſtance that euer could juſtly bee ſhewed: may it pleaſe your Highnes to conſider that there be<note n="b" place="margin">Three vvaies of triall.</note> three wayes for a prudent and circumſpect Maſter, to trie out the honeſty, and fidelity of his ſeruant accuſed of treachery.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Former beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</note>The firſt, by making inquiſition of his former life and behauiour, what Maſter he ſerued before, in what eſtate, and for howe long time, and with what ſucceſſe and truſtines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Preſent car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note>The ſecond, to looke narrowly into his preſent quality and carriage, and to be aſſured howe he is and hath beene affected to him, his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, friendes, and dependers.</p>
               <p>The laſt, to compare his actions and comportments, aſwell paſt as preſent, with thoſe that traduce him; and to ſee what caution he can giue (to ſtoppe his enemies ſuggeſtions) for his future fidelitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21675:11"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Compariſon betvveene the Catholikes &amp; nevv Clergies comportments</note> To this forme of triall (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) we ſubmit our ſelues, our liues and actions, and will indeauoure to giue you full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in all the foreſaid points of our carriage: <hi>Vt obſtruatur os loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium iniqua,</hi> to the end that the mouth of him that ſpeaketh wicked things may be ſtopt, that you may (not withſtanding what exclamations ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to the contrary) ſerue your ſelfe of our poore forces, liues, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, in all your fortunes and imployments againſt all your foes and enemies whoſoeuer.</p>
               <p>To beginne then where we left when your <hi>Maieſty</hi> made your happy enteraunce into this Realme, and to put you in minde by what degrees, and for what deſertes wee were brought into that miſerable eſtate your Highnes found vs in. It is well knowne that before our impriſonment and reſtraint, vpon the ſtatute of recuſancy, for the only Teſtemony of our conſciences, ſome of vs did beare offices in the common wealth, and were dignified by the late <hi>Queene:</hi> in which charges and negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (without vaunt be it ſaid) our carriages were<note n="b" place="margin">Catholike behauiours be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainte &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace for recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancy.</note> ciuill, laudable, and loyall; and ſome of vs liued without charge, yet not without credit and eſtimation, of worſhipfull and honeſt men, and were aſwell accepted &amp; reputed in the Countries and Prouinces where we dwelt, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment in, as were any other of our neighbours of the like calling and degrees.</p>
               <p>After our reſtraint our<note n="c" place="margin">Their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanure after their reſtrainte</note> behauiour was ſuch as became <hi>Catholike Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> ſubjects towardes <hi>Christian</hi> Magiſtrates, with all humility, reſpect, modeſtie, and ſubjection; euer either readylie doing what they enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or patiently ſuffering what they impoſed.</p>
               <p>The long time of our perſecutions: the number of them that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: the diuerſity of their rankes &amp; qualities, and of their humors and diſpoſitions: the perpetuity and variety of temptations &amp; tribulations: the infinite indignities we paſſed thorowe for ſo many yeares, if they had fallen out among any other conſtitutions of men then <hi>Catholike,</hi> they might haue wroung (very probably) out of men well mortified &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, ſome action of diſlike, or perilous practize of diſcontentment, when ſuch multitudes of all degrees were ſo aſſayled; eſpecially of people ſo reſolute in that ſupreameſt degree of fortitude: which is as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> defineth it, <hi>Triſtia pro virtute tollerare,</hi> to indure heauy thinges for vertues ſake, a point very dangerous, and whereof there want not plenty of lamentable euents, riſing from caſes of deſperate neceſſity: which <hi>Abner</hi> the generall of <hi>Saules</hi> armie objected to <hi>Ioab Dauids Lieuten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>Exclamauit</hi> Abner <hi>ad</hi> Ioab <hi>&amp; ait:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reg. 2 cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>num vſque ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternecionem tuus mucro d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaeuiet? an ignoras quod</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Deſperatio periculoſa.</note> 
                  <hi>periculoſa eſt deſperatio? vſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21675:12"/>
non dicis populo vt omittat perſequi fratres ſuos?</hi> And <hi>Abner</hi> cried out to <hi>Ioab,</hi> ſhall thy ſword be cruell euen to the death? Knoweſt thou not that deſperation is perilous? Why doſt not thou commaund the people that they ceaſe to perſecute their brethren?</p>
               <p>But this may wee glory in, (REDOVBTED SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNE) that in all this time, no diligence of our Aduerſaries, no Malice, no Polecy, no Curioſity, no Argus eyes (of which there was great ſtore, greedely prying into all our doinges) could euer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpie the leaſt ſhadowe of diſloyaltie, in any one action of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like weales profeſſors and moſt ſufferers in the cauſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the long and perpetuall courſe of their ſeruitudes and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The true reaſon whereof is, the Doctrine we are taught by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which wee profeſſe; which telleth vs, that we muſt obey our Princes: <hi>Non propter iram, ſed propter conſcientiam:</hi> not for anie indignation, but for conſcience ſake; and that to reſiſt them, is to reſiſt Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce: and this is the bitte and bridle that euery true <hi>Catholike</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth in his mouth, to reſtrayne him from that by grace and feare of Gods judgementes, which fleſh and bloud otherwiſe with the liuely ſence and feeling of inſupportable miſeries and afflictions, might driue him vnto.</p>
               <p>In this caſe of our<note n="a" place="margin">The laye Catholikes fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the late Queene.</note> dutifull behauiour in the late <hi>Queenes</hi> dayes, <hi>fiant immici nostri iudices,</hi> let our enemies be our judges therein: let the Roles, Regiſters, and Recordes ſpeake, ſithence the great penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties impoſed vpon vs for recuſancy, what hath beene our Innocency, our Integrity; our vnimpeachable carriage and demeanour: how free we haue beene from the leaſt ſuſpition of treaſon and practiſe, as it pleaſed the Lordes of the late priuie Councell to tell vs,<note n="b" place="margin">Catholikes iuſtified by the Lordes of the Councell.</note> 
                  <hi>that the reaſon of our impriſonment was not in reſpect of any doubt made of our loyalties, but only to preuent the</hi> Spaniardes <hi>hopes of our aſſiſtance in their pretended inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the yeare<note n="c" place="margin">The carriage of Catholikes the yeare 88.</note> Eightie-eight, when the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> came with inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion to inuade this Realme, our offers at <hi>Eely</hi> to the Lord <hi>North</hi> (then Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> in thoſe partes) in the preſence of the <hi>Deane</hi> of <hi>Fely,</hi> and many others elſe of worſhippefull calling there preſent at that time, for the haſting away of the forces of thoſe Countries to <hi>Tilbery-Camp,</hi> were theſe: wee beſeeched and inſtantly importuned, that wee might be imployed in thoſe ſeruices, in the defence of our Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and not indure that diſhonour, that the whole Realme ſhould be indaungered, and we no vnworthy members thereof and no meane
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21675:12"/>
freehoulders, ſhould be exempted from that ſo behoofefull and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſeruice: wee with voluntary aduenture of our liues and worldly fortunes<note n="a" place="margin">Their offer of ſeruice in perſon.</note> offered to ſerue in Perſon with our Sonnes, Seruants, and Tennantes, at our owne charges; as deſirous moſt joyfully to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that oportunitie, to make manifeſt our loyalties in our Prince and Countries cauſe: we deſired to be placed in the firſt front of the battaile: wee offered to ſerue in the places of the hotteſt and moſt dangerous ſeruice: and if we might not obtaine that fauour of truſt and ſeruice, for greater ſecurity, and liuely demonſtration of our true <hi>Engliſh</hi> hartes, we did offer, and implore to be placed<note n="b" place="margin">They offer to bee placed vnarmed in the forefront of the battaile.</note> vnarmed in our ſhirts, before the formoſt ranckes of our battailes, to receiue in our bodies the firſt volly of our enemies ſhotte, to leaue an vndoubted Teſtemony by that our death to ſtoppe the mouthes of the ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine maligners of our vnſpotted integrity, and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>But if none of theſe inſtant requeſtes would bee graunted vs, yet thoſe handes vvhich ſhould haue valorouſly beene vſed againſt the enemie, ſhould bee zealouſly lifted vp to God for the deliuery of our Prince and Countrie, and to obtayne renowned glorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt the Inuador; wherein wee failed not, anſwereable to the dutie of loyaleſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjectes, all which was offered by vs to bee performed, notwithſtanding the late <hi>Queene</hi> was twice<note n="c" place="margin">They plaie the partes of good ſubiects notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding al excom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munications.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated. And this is a demonſtrable and vndoubted argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that wee are not conditionall Subjectes, a calumny ſo frequent in the mouthes of the Miniſtry, and by them endleſly objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</p>
               <p>The like offer to that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> at <hi>Eelie</hi> made, the<note n="d" place="margin">The like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer made the L. Vaux.</note> Lord <hi>Vaux</hi> (then priſoner likewiſe, for Teſtemony of his conſcience, vnder the charge of the <hi>Arch-biſhoppe</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) offered, and in like ſort would haue donne all the <hi>Catholikes</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> vpon like occaſion and opportunity.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> was diſperſed, and their forces defeated, the <hi>Vice-Chauncellor</hi> of <hi>Cambridge</hi> aſſociated with the <hi>Deane</hi> of <hi>Eelie,</hi> ſent to <hi>Eelie</hi> to the <hi>Catholike</hi> recuſants there impriſoned, from the Lords of <hi>Queene Elizabethes</hi> priuie Councel, with<note n="e" place="margin">A forme of ſubmiſsion ſent dovvne to the Catholike from the Councell.</note> a forme of proteſtation of their dutie and allegeance, penned by the ſaid <hi>Queenes</hi> learned Councell, with direction and commiſsion to take the ſaid recuſants ſubſcriptions thereunto, being altogither vnexpected of them, they being cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and hauing no intelligence at all of any Commiſioners reparing to them: So ſoone as theſe Commiſsioners had read ſome part of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21675:13"/>
commiſſion to the <hi>Catholikes</hi> there, they forth with were ſeuerally deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and in cloſe priſon reſtrayned. And notwithſtanding the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall originall ſent purpoſely for them to ſubſcribe vnto: yet the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners (as it ſeemed for a more triall, or for a more aduantage taking againſt the <hi>Catholikes</hi> there) taxed euery of them to ſet downe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the proteſtation of their allegeance and dutie, to like purpoſe as was ſet forth in the originall ſent to them from the Lordes of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, which the <hi>Catholike</hi> Gentlemen were permitted to haue but one only time read vnto them. This ſeuerall forme of ſubmiſſion in ſuch ſtrict order exacted by the Commiſſioners, was in that<note n="a" place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes exhibite a forme of ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion farre more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete then that vvhich vvas ſent them.</note> ample manner performed by the ſaid recuſants, that the ſaid Commiſſioners (ſinguler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extolling and greatly preferring the ſame, before the ſaid originall) accepted thereof, and required not at all the <hi>Catholikes</hi> to ſubſcribe to the ſaid originall ſo penned by the ſaid <hi>Queenes</hi> learned Councell, &amp; addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Lordes of the priuie Councell: to whome the ſaid proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being ſent, and by them peruſed, they receiued ſuch a full appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, that after that time neuer any odious imputation or calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the fidelity of the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> preuayled.</p>
               <p>The like was the valour,<note n="b" place="margin">The fidelity of Iriſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</note> fidelity, &amp; laudable ſeruice of the <hi>Iriſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> recuſants at <hi>Kinſale</hi> in <hi>Ireland, Anno</hi> 1600. who joyning their forces with the late <hi>Queenes</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> powre, and againſt their owne Countrimen &amp; Kinſmen, expelled with their aſſiſtaunce, the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and were ſpeciall meanes to keepe <hi>Ireland</hi> in obedience to the Crowne of <hi>England:</hi> which otherwiſe (in the opinions of the Commaunders of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> forces then there) had beene vtterly loſt. And none of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there doubted, but that it was in the power of thoſe <hi>Iriſh Catholike Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen</hi> and their followers, to haue betrayed then that Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the hands of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> if either zeale of extirping the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> religion thence, and firme eſtabliſhing of the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion, could haue preuayled with them; or dread of<note n="c" place="margin">Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred not the Iriſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes to doe the duties of good ſubiects.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, or threatning of the powerfull inuader, proclayming by ſound of Trumpet, and deuulging proclamations that his ſword ſhould no more ſpare a <hi>Catholike</hi> recuſante diſobeying that excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, then it ſhould doe a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> reſiſting in armes. And this ſinguler act of loyaltie, ſo ſhortly after ſeconding and confirming the like of the <hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi> in Eighty-eight, without all gayne-ſaying conuinceth, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Catholike</hi> recuſants, are not<note n="d" place="margin">Engliſh and Iriſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes.</note> condicionall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but moſt true loyall and faithfull ſubjects to their Prince, and to the Crowne of <hi>England;</hi> therein giuing place to no ſubjects of thoſe two Realmes whoſoeuer, or of what degree ſoeuer: and whoſe proofe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21675:13"/>
and triall herein, farre excelleth all other the ſubjects of thoſe Realmes; if preheminence ſhould in that behalfe be attributed to any profeſſion of Religion in the ſaid Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>This argument of our former behauiour, and of our obedience vnder the ſeueritie of the late <hi>Queene,</hi> may in all reaſon aſſure your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> that in matter of our loyaltie we are like pure Gold, fined and refined in the fine of many yeares probation, and therein not to be any way ſtayned.</p>
               <p>The ſecond triall of our fidelities conſiſteth in matter likewiſe of fact<note n="a" place="margin">Catholikes behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes his Maieſties Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors and him ſelfe.</note> towardes your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Predeceſſors, your Title in them, and in your ſelfe, and the effect of our loue and affection performed in all occaſions, that might giue contentment to your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> both before and ſince your entraunce into this your Kingdome of <hi>England;</hi> which we will endeauour to touch as briefly as we can.</p>
               <p>It cannot be denied then in the firſt ranke of theſe our comporte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but that we our ſelues in our times, and our <hi>Catholike</hi> Parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs at all times of opportunity offered, haue declared our deuouted affections to your ſaid Highnes<note n="b" place="margin">Catholikes alvvayes affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the K. Title to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> right to this Crowne, the teſtemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies whereof are in printed bookes and publike facts ſo manifeſt to the world, that we neede not long dwell on that point: vouchſafe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore patience we beſeech you (DEARE SOVERAIGNE) to heare ſome inſtances of the<note n="c" place="margin">Bleſſinges &amp; benefittes his Maieſty hath receiued by Catholikes.</note> bleſſinges and the benefits your <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and by our ſeruices and fidelities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>King Henry</hi> the vij<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> and his eldeſt Daughter (from whome your <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath receiued lineally and directly your birth, right, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſucceſſion to this Crowne) were moſt zealous and religious <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes:</hi> and for that ſinguler affection he did beare to the<note n="d" place="margin">Henry the 7. preferreth the Scotiſh King before the Frenſh.</note> 
                  <hi>Scotiſh</hi> nation, principally for their great zeale at all times to the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion, preferred the ſame before <hi>Fraunce,</hi> beſtowing his ſaid eldeſt Daughter on your Highnes great <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> and the younger vpon the <hi>French King,</hi> by which happy marriage came that lineall and rightfull deſcent of bloud, that made your <hi>Maieſties</hi> renowned <hi>Mother</hi> Heyre apparant to this Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> who alſo was the vndoubted<note n="e" place="margin">His Maieſties Mother lineall heire to King Edvvard the Confeſſor.</note> lineall Heire to <hi>King Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> by his ſiſter <hi>Margaret, Queene</hi> and <hi>Saint;</hi> and conſequently your <hi>Maiesty</hi> from your <hi>Catholike Mother,</hi> and her <hi>Catholike</hi> Predeceſſors, hath not only receiued the hereditary ſucceſſion of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but alſo a double right to the Crowne of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as<note n="f" place="margin">His Maieſtie true heire both to the Saxon &amp; Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man Princes.</note> heire to the <hi>Saxon</hi> lineall line by a holy <hi>Saint</hi> &amp; <hi>Catholike Queene,</hi> and heire to the <hi>Norman</hi> line by a moſt worthy <hi>Catholike</hi> Prince, and a bleſſed <hi>Martir,</hi> and all them vnited in her, and nowe duly deſcended to your <hi>Maieſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21675:14"/>
                  <note place="margin">Queene Mary</note>It was the pious and vertuous <hi>Queene Mary</hi> and her <hi>Catholike</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who cancelled the forged will of her <hi>Father King Henry</hi> the eight, exceeding preiudiciall to your right in this Crowne, that diſproued it in Parliament, and depoſed the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> vſurping <hi>Queene Iane</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Queene Iane ſet vp by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</note> ſet vp then by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to the diſinheriting of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> and <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> and his eldeſt ſiſters iſſue, vvho was your <hi>Maieſties</hi> great <hi>Grand-mother,</hi> and whoſe iſſue were in all right to haue beene preferred before her younger ſiſter, <hi>Grand-mother</hi> to the vſurping <hi>Proteſtant Queene Iane;</hi> who ſo depoſed by that renowned pious <hi>Catholike Queene Mary,</hi> the Crowne (by her royall prouidence) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to the rightfull, and lawfull heires thereof, conſequently deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nowe to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> conformable to the lawe of God, Nature, and Nations.</p>
               <p>The ſerpentine inuectiue made by <hi>Hales</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Queene Elizabethes</hi> raigne, directly againſt your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Title, thereby intending<note n="b" place="margin">Hales inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue againſt the Title of Scotland.</note> the aduauncement of a pretender, potently in thoſe daies poſſeſſed in the breaſtes of no meane multitudes, was vpon the ſetting forth thereof in the time of <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> indelayedly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, fully anſwered, &amp; learnedly confuted by<note n="c" place="margin">Hales anſvve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red by Iuſtice Brovvne &amp; M. Ployden both Catholikes.</note> Sir <hi>Anthony Browne</hi> then one of the Iuſtices of the common Pleas, and lately before in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> raigne had beene chiefe Iuſtice of the ſame Court, and M. <hi>Edmund Ployden</hi> famous Lawyers, with the aſſent of other <hi>Catholike</hi> Diuines, ciuill Lawyers, and Gentlemen of good worth, judgement, and experience.</p>
               <p>Howe many<note n="d" place="margin">Havvardes, Perſies, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, Vaux, Treſhams, Throghmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Abington</note> families of <hi>Catholikes</hi> haue endured great damages and detrimentes in renowne and ſtate, for deſire they had to maintaine the right of your moſt bleſſed <hi>Mothers</hi> Title in remainder, and aduentures made to relieue her, and deliuer the afflicted Princeſſe out of her cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity; with much abundant loue, teares, and affection, your ſacred mother teſtified publiquely at the end of her life.</p>
               <p>Since your <hi>Mothers</hi> death, we remayned euer<note n="e" place="margin">Catholikes behauiour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Maieſties Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> conſtant to your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> right to the ſucceſsion of this Crowne, not ebbing and flowing in our affections, but reſolute euer to liue or die with your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in that moſt juſt pretence: but if any particular perſon in forraigne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries hath ſpoken or written to the contrary, for his priuate and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular pretentions, he is to anſwere for himſelfe, and his owne fact, for therein we diſclaime: which party (as we are credibly enformed) hath both before and ſithence the <hi>Queenes</hi> death, done great diligence to giue your <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſatisfaction. And your <hi>Maieſty</hi> is not ignorant, (we are aſſured) what hath beene the carriage, opinion, and oppoſition
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21675:14"/>
of vs and our friendes euen in that particuler in the fauour and defence of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> right, both within and without the Realme: what <note n="a" place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, vvhich M. Charles Paget, Cap. Treſham, M. Iohn Stonor of Stonor, and diuers others ſuffred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, are noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</note> dangers we haue paſſed at home, and what ſlaunders and damages ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many of our <hi>Catholike</hi> brethren haue ſuffered abroade, for ſhewing themſelues <hi>Scotiſh</hi> in faction (as we were tearmed, that<note n="b" place="margin">Scotiſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction vvhat.</note> is firmely, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueably affected to your <hi>Maieſties</hi> right of ſucceſſion to this Crowne.) your <hi>Maieſty</hi> haue heard, and we haue felt and ſhall feele, our honours and eſtates thereby being extreamely diminiſhed and eclipſed whiles we liue, vnleſſe your <hi>Maieſties</hi> pious &amp; royall hart vouchſafe to repaire and relieue the ſame.</p>
               <p>Neither did your <hi>Maieſties</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">His Maieſties zeale in the Proteſtants Religion did nothing dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes his right and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</note> zeale in the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> religion, any way alter or diminiſh the juſt conceit, and dutifull conſideration we carried to that juſtice and right, which God and nature had prepared for you from your cradell.</p>
               <p>If then our carriage and affection to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> was ſuch, when your Religion was to ours ſo different, your Perſon to vs vnknowne, your fortune doubtfull, the factions diuers, the oppoſitions in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood very great, and the euent of your affaires very vncertaine: what may your <hi>Maieſty</hi> preſume of vs nowe? or rather what may you not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, &amp; aſſure to your ſelfe of our fidelities, in this time of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> preſent proſperity, and fruition of this Crowne, hauing proued our ſelues ſo faithfull to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> in times of your expectations?</p>
               <p>And to conclude, ſuch is the<note n="d" place="margin">The confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes haue in his maieſties royall dealing vvith them.</note> confidence we haue in your <hi>Maieſties</hi> clemency, and ſo farre we rely vpon the bountie of your nature and royall proceeding with vs, that whereas the not payment of twentie poundes a moneth for recuſancy into the Exchequor, (at the tearmes by lawe preſcribed) putteth vs abſolutely into your <hi>Maieſties</hi> hands and mercie, for two partes of all our landes and reuenues during our liues, and maketh vs a pray to the diſcretion of our enemies &amp; promotors, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling vs to ſell our goods, to let or ſet our lands for our reliefe, to make joyntures for the maintenance of our wiues, or eſtate of landes to our children, albeit by not payment of the ſaid ſummes at the tearmes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid wee fell within the lapſes of the Lawes in ſuch extreamitie of daunger, that our caſe was not to bee releeued but by ſpeciall act of Parliament: yet ſuch of vs, as at <hi>Wilton</hi> in <hi>Nouember</hi> laſt paſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Lordes of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> moſt honourable priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, to be ſecured from the ſaid forfeiture; which otherwiſe we were to incurre in default of payment, as is before ſayde, they were (farre beſides their expectation) taxed by the Lordes of a kinde of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, or chalenging your <hi>Maieſty</hi> with breach of promiſe for the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21675:15"/>
vs of the ſaid mulcte-money, in ſort as it was deliuered vs in Iulie precedent at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> whereupon wee reſolued abſolutely to put our whole Eſtate into your <hi>Maieſties</hi> handes, that your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may ſee, how wee preferre the credit and confidence wee haue in your <hi>Maieſties</hi> juſtice, equity, conſcience, and mercie, before our owne ſecuritie, our landes, goodes, and liuinges; and ſo doe wee ſtill remayne in the ſame predicament: where if euery pennie had beene a pound, &amp; euerie of our mole-hilles mountaynes, wee would (vpon ſuch vrging of our diffidence) haue proſtrated all the ſame at your moſt Royall <hi>Maieſties</hi> feete.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 6.</hi> Ths carriage and behauiour of our Accuſers.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The carriage of our Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſtes.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T reſteth now laſtly to conſider what hath beene the behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of ſome of our accuſers (the <hi>Miniſters</hi> we meane, &amp; ſome hotte ſpirits of their adherentes and followers) from time to time in your <hi>Maieſties</hi> affaires (that hath ſo cheriſhed, dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and aduaunced them) and to other their lawfull <hi>Princes,</hi> that haue not ſo fully concurred with them in matter of religion as your <hi>Maieſty</hi> doth, <hi>vt contraria iuxta ſe poſita magis cluceſcant,</hi> that contraries compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether may the more cleerelie appeare.</p>
               <p>If you demaund what they were that accounted it a matter treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to retaine any booke or paper in fauour of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Title, and that in publike bookes called your <hi>Mothers</hi> right to this Crowne a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Title. <hi>Agendum eſt obſignatis tabulis:</hi> and we muſt needs tell you that it was a Student of <hi>Lyons Inne</hi> a Lawer by profeſſion, and a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in Religion, that in a booke printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1584. &amp; intituled (<hi>A diſcouery of treaſons againſt the</hi> Queenes Majeſty <hi>by</hi> Fraunces Throgmorton) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other his treaſons,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</note> he reckoneth this for one in theſe wordes. <hi>There were alſo found among other his papers</hi> 12. <hi>petegrees of the deſcent of the Crowne of</hi> England <hi>printed and publiſhed by the Biſhoppe of</hi> Roſſe <hi>in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the pretended Title of the</hi> Scotiſh Queene <hi>his</hi> Miſtris. What could be more vnjuſt and iniurious to that bleſſed <hi>Lady</hi> and all her poſteritie, then in a booke printed in defence of an execution of juſtice, to call her Title falſe pretented and vnjuſt, and account the euidences and recordes thereof as treaſon in the higheſt degree?</p>
               <p>If inquiry be made who they were that in prejudice of your <hi>Maieſties</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21675:15"/>
right to this Crowne did ſet vp the vſurping <hi>Queene Iane,</hi> deſcended from the younger ſiſter of your <hi>Maieſties</hi> great <hi>Grand-Mother,</hi> that was the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt daughter to <hi>King Henry</hi> the vij<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Our hiſtories tell vs that they were <note n="a" place="margin">The Duke of Nothumb. the Dukes of Somerſet, Suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>folke, &amp; other Proteſtants, &amp; all the Proteſt. Biſhops Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, of K. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie.</note> enemies to the <hi>Catholike</hi> faith which we profeſſe, &amp; the firſt aduauncers of the newe Religion in this Country.</p>
               <p>If we call to minde the complotters and compaſſers of the murther committed on the Perſon of your Highnes<note n="b" place="margin">His maieſties Father and Grand-father ſlayne.</note> 
                  <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> and the barbarous butchering of your <hi>Mothers</hi> Secretary in her Royall preſence, and the miraculous eſcape of your Graces perſon by Gods ſinguler protection, when a<note n="c" place="margin">His Maieſty purſued in his Mothers vvombe, and miraculouſly preſerued.</note> chardged piſtoll put to your <hi>Mothers</hi> wombe by one of the traytorous race of the <hi>Gowries,</hi> to haue diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you both at one blowe, could not giue fire; we finde by the printed monumentes of <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Annales that the actors, authors, and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of thoſe tragedies were not of the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion.</p>
               <p>If we demaund who they were that tooke<note n="d" place="margin">The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery authors of theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes.</note> armes againſt your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> gratious <hi>Mother,</hi> that ouerthrewe her in the field, that layd violent handes vpon her ſacred Perſon, and impriſoned her in <hi>Lawghleuen,</hi> that depriued her of her Crowne, and expelled her out of her Kingdome, and procured afterwardes her captiuitie in this Realme: no man is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that the<note n="e" place="margin">The Earle of Moray. Knox the Cataline of Scotland.</note> Baſtard of <hi>Scotland</hi> with the Presbitery &amp; that runnegate Fryer <hi>Iohn Knox,</hi> mortall enemies to all order, rule, and authority, were the Architects of theſe deteſtable actions.</p>
               <p>Howe zealous<note n="f" place="margin">Bothvvell &amp; Govvry, tvvo pillers of the Presbitery.</note> 
                  <hi>Bothwell</hi> and <hi>Gowry</hi> were againſt poore <hi>Catholikes;</hi> and what pillers and patrons they were of the Presbitery, the world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> by experience can beſt teſtifie what perilous, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, and ſeditious members they were of the common wealth, and howe often your ſacred Perſon was indaungered by them, and others of their profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we hope that we may without offence to any, confidently affirme, that they were not <hi>Catholikes</hi> that cauſed your <hi>Mothers</hi> vntimely death: the memory of which times, for many reſpects we had forborne to touch, but only to remoue the odious and vnjuſt imputations, diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the time of this preſent ſeſſion of Parliament againſt vs in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne libell, or rather a clamorous calumnions inuectiue, publiſhed in this preſent ſeſſion of Parliament, againſt a moſt modeſt, learned, and ſubmiſſiue ſupplication dedicated to your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in <hi>March</hi> laſt: where the Libeller calleth <hi>Catholikes</hi> to the Barre, and would haue then indigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and paſſe their triall for that matter:<note n="g" place="margin">Sutclifes ovvne vvordes in the 8. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his ſaid libell.</note> 
                  <hi>Which done</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>his</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty <hi>may eaſely perceiue that they are to be hated, and abhorred as cauſers and contriuers of all his</hi> Mothers <hi>troubles and calamities, his proofes are the authour
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21675:16"/>
of the</hi> Ieſuites <hi>Catechiſme</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">The authour of that Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueterat enemy of that order &amp; therfore more credulous then conuenient in matter of theirs diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> written in diſgrace of that order, which booke is of as great credit (with men of tender conſciences, and vpright car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in matter of truth and equitie) as <hi>Lucians</hi> Dialogues, <hi>Watſons</hi> Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets, or <hi>Eſopes</hi> fables, and what this Catechiſte wrote of priuate paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without any authenticall warrant, this libeller doth vrge with the like perturbation. And here (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) we might as readely, as liuely, produce a world of inuinceable proofes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of this libeller, by prouing the actors of that complotment and tragicall proceeding not to haue beene any one of them <hi>Catholikes,</hi> or their well-willers, but (we carefully ſhunning to charge any with bloudy imbrumentes in that lamentable fact of <hi>Englands</hi> agony,) and only to free our ſelues from that moſt odious, impudent, and falfe calumniation, wee ſoly reſort to matter of higheſt record, dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant to bee ſeene of all men in publike printed ſtatutes, being the fore-runners of that ſtrange execution of your bleſſed and moſt glorious <hi>Mother.</hi> Whereby it is moſt euident and well knowne <hi>(etiam lippis &amp; ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus)</hi> to blinde men &amp; barbers, that they were not <hi>Catholikes</hi> that made and enacted thoſe ſtatutes of the thirtenth of <hi>Queene Elizabethes</hi> Raigne, for the<note n="b" place="margin">13. Elizabeth Limitation of the right of the Crovvne.</note> limitation of the right of the Crowne, to the diſpoſition of the Lords and Parliament from the free right and courſe of bloud and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. That made it treaſon in the ſame Parliament, to<note n="c" place="margin">Treaſon to ſay that the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons Titles &amp; poſſibilities of all pretenders to the crovvne be not ſubiect to the actes made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> hould or ſay that the common lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and ſtatutes to be made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not of ſufficient validity to gouerne the perſons, and to binde and limitte the Titles of any that hath any poſſibility to the Crowne.</p>
               <p>They were not <hi>Catholikes</hi> that made it treaſon in the ſame Parliament,<note n="d" place="margin">Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, treaſon.</note> to abſolue from ſinne and reconcile, or to be ſo abſolued or reconciled.<note n="e" place="margin">Agnus Dei, Beades, or Croſſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire.</note> A premunire to bring in any tookens called <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> or Croſſes, Pictures, or halowed Beades, or to haue or receiue them.</p>
               <p>They were not <hi>Catholikes</hi> that the 23. of <hi>Queene Elizabethes</hi> Raigne made it treaſon<note n="f" place="margin">23. Elizabeth treaſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvade men to the Catholike religion.</note> to perſwade men to the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion, and the loſſe of 200. markes to heare<note n="g" place="margin">200 markes for laing, 100 markes for hearing a mas.</note> 
                  <hi>Maſſe,</hi> or to pay xx. pound monethly for<note n="h" place="margin">xx. pound a moneth for re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſancy.</note> refuſing to goe to the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſeruice: or the forfeits of x. pound monethly for ſuch as ſhould keepe any<note n="i" place="margin">x. pound a moneth for keeping a ſchoolmaſter.</note> Schoolmaſter not allowed by the Biſhoppe of the Dioces, and refuſing to goe to Church.</p>
               <p>They were not <hi>Catholikes</hi> who made an act 27. of the ſaid <hi>Queene</hi> by vertue whereof your gratious<note n="k" place="margin">27. Eliz. the act vvas made vvhich cauſed the death of his Maieſties Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
                  <hi>Mother</hi> loſt her life; and in the ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it was made treaſon for all<note n="l" place="margin">In the ſame yeare it vvas made treaſon to be a Prieſt and come in or remaine in the land, &amp; felony to receiue or releeue them.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſts</hi> or Religious men that had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken orders by any forraigne authority, to remayne or come into this Kingdome, and fellony to relieue or entertayne them.</p>
               <p>It was made treaſon to be brought vp in the Seminaries, premunire
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21675:16"/>
to ſend thither any reliefe.</p>
               <p>In the 28. of the ſaid <hi>Queene,</hi> it was enacted that the two partes of the landes and leaſes of ſuch recuſantes, as ſhould faile to pay the xx. pound a moneth in the Exchequor at the tearmes prefixed, ſhould be ſeazed into the <hi>Queenes</hi> handes.</p>
               <p>In the 35. it was enacted that euery<note n="m" place="margin">25. Elizab. certayne recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants vvere by an act then made to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure the realme</note> recuſant aboue the age of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares, being not worth twentie markes (exceeding his confined limittes) ſhould abjure the Realme, and if he refuſed to abjure or retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after abjuration, to be accounted a fellon.</p>
               <p>Item that the partie ſhould pay ten pound a moneth that<note n="n" place="margin">Ten pound a moneth for keeping a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant in the hovvſe.</note> keepes any recuſant in his howſe after warning.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Parliament, recuſantes are<note n="o" place="margin">The ſame yeare vvas the ſtatute of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finementes enacted.</note> reſtrayned to their certayne vſuall, and common places of abode, and are not to remoue aboue fiue miles thence without licence of the Biſhoppe and two Iuſtices, vpon payne of forfeiting of all their goodes, and all their free and coppyhold landes, and annuities during life: &amp; all ſuch recuſants that had not landes of twentie markes value by yeare, or goodes of fourtie pound, if they conformed not themſelues, or repayred not to their places of limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall abjure the Realme. By the courſe and contriuing of ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall and cruell lawes at the ſame time, and in the ſame ſeſſions, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well againſt <hi>Catholikes,</hi> as againſt your gratious <hi>Mother;</hi> it ſeemeth by all probability (to perſons eſteemed of judgement &amp; great experience, in the inſight of worldly driftes both in this Realme, and in forraigne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions) that the principal marke which was aymed at in thoſe times, was at the ſelfe ſame ſeaſon by ſeuerity and ſhadowe of the ſame lawes an inſtance to ruinate &amp; ouerthrowe the<note n="p" place="margin">The perſon of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Mother her right and Title and the Catholikes, cauſe, all ſhotte at by the ſame lavves, and at the ſame time.</note> perſon of your gratious <hi>Mother</hi> and her right, and the profeſſors of the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion; ſuppoſing that thoſe three muſt either ſtand or fall togither of neceſſitie: but <hi>non eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium contra Dominum:</hi> there is no councell againſt God: her right &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity hath (God betha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked) preuayled, &amp; the poore <hi>Catholikes</hi> from that time to this, the more they haue beene oppreſſed, the more they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, which cannot fall out otherwiſe, vnleſſe it proue falſe which God hath ſaid by the mouth of his Saints and ſeruants: <hi>Precioſa in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu Domini mors Sanctorum eius,</hi> pretious in the ſight of our Lord is the death of his Saints. <hi>Et ſanguis Martirum ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> the bloud of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, the ſeede of the Church. We accuſe no man in particuler in this caſe, and could haue beene content: <hi>vlcus hoc intactum leuiter pertranſire,</hi> to haue ſleightly paſt ouer this boch vntouched, but that this reſpondent would needes deale with vs, as <hi>Putifars</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">The libeller like Ioſeph his Miſtris &amp; Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſannas iudges.</note> wife did with holy <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> or the carnall judges with the chaſte <hi>Suſanna, (viz.)</hi> put vs to our plunges, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21675:17"/>
purgations for ſuch crimes, as were proper and peculiar to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>Neuer was it heard of that in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> any <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> euer ſuffred any thing for that gratious <hi>Lady,</hi> or your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Title, but infinite are the<note n="a" place="margin">In Scotland, Setons, Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Simples, Maxuelles.</note> families of the <hi>Catholikes</hi> that haue ſuffered for them both. As the <hi>Seatons,</hi> the <hi>Gordens,</hi> the <hi>Simples,</hi> the <hi>Maxuells</hi> in <hi>Scotland:</hi> the<note n="b" place="margin">In England, Havvards, Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſies, Pagettes, Treſhammes, Throgmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Abing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Winſor.</note> 
                  <hi>Hawards, Perſies, Vauxes, Pagets, Treſhams, Throgmortons, Winſors, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisburie, Abington,</hi> and diuers other worthy Gentlemen in this Land, the ſhipwrackes of whoſe opulent abundant ſtates and fortunes, are inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible teſtemonies of the Libellers falſehood and follie in this his obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and of the conſtant fidelity of <hi>Catholikes</hi> to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> and all your race and predeceſſors, in all their fortunes whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>And thus your <hi>Maieſty</hi> doth ſee the compariſon of our former times, and our precedent behauiours, with our preſent affection and future aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance: If then we be not rewarded, and reſpected as all others are of other profeſſions that haue done their duties, as we did, in aduauncing your <hi>Maieſties</hi> affaires, and acknowledging your rightfull Authority: yet at the leaſt we hope that it will not be thought reaſonable, that we ſhould be left in the ſame maſſe of miſery, which your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> found vs in at your entrance.</p>
               <p>Make vs then (SWEETE SOVERAIGNE) as able as we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſerue you, not by newe dignities and authorities, but by reſtoring vs to our priſtine honours, and honeſt reputations, and to our birth-right freedome, and liberty by your only Peerles juſtice, clemency, and benignity; permitting vs to liue in peace, <hi>&amp; comedere buccellam noſtram ſine dolore,</hi> to put a bitte of meate into our mouthes without ſorrowe, without frights, without ſlights, and without circumuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Aduerſaries: our woundes are ſo deepe and dangerous in matters of our honours, ſtates, and liberties, that no Phiſition can cure vs but your ſelf with the ſoueraigne balme of your renowned Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. What pleaſure or profit can redowne to your <hi>Maieſties</hi> perſon or eſtate, if we your approued and aſſured ſeruants and ſubjectes rotte in priſon, die in baniſhment, and liue in penurie and diſgrace; for no other crime or offence, but for the conſtant profeſsion of that Religion, which in conſcience we are perſwaded to be the only true worſhippe of God, &amp; ſaluation of our ſoules? Of which our faith and beliefe, we haue ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſo ſufficient reaſon, that we hope, it will fully ſatisfie and content, ſo wiſe, learned, politique, and diſcreete a Prince, as your <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath ſhewed your ſelfe to be in all occaſions preſented to make triall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which maketh vs the more confident in our juſt and reaſonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21675:17"/>
becauſe we ſue to a moſt wiſe, juſt, and learned <hi>Monarch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit more then this can hardly be required of men, whoſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delities are ſo ſufficiently tried and teſtefied (as appeareth by the whole ſubſtance and tennor of this our <hi>Apologie</hi>) yet <hi>pro abundantiore cautela,</hi> we humbly lay downe at your <hi>Maieſties</hi> feete this forme of ſubmiſsion, and ſecurity following, in behalfe of our Prieſts and Paſtors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER 7.</hi> The forme of the Catholikes ſubmiſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we may be permitted to enjoy ſome quiet, graue,<note place="margin">The lay Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note> and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Clergie men for the comfort of our ſoules, we doubt not but to giue your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> a farre greater ſecurity for the fewe hundreds of our <hi>Prieſts,</hi> then was giuen for the many thouſands of <hi>Queene Maries Prieſts,</hi> and Prelates in the late <hi>Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethes</hi> dayes; againſt whome, albeit aboue<note n="a" place="margin">10000 Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie men lefte their liuings, rather then they vvould leaue their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> ten thouſand of them, did abandon their Eccleſiaſticall Liuinges, rather then they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues to the times (eſpecially the<note n="b" place="margin">All Queene Mary Biſhops forſooke their Prelatures, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they vvould forſake their chiefe Paſtor.</note> holy Senate of Biſhops, no one excepted) yet in the time of the ſaid <hi>Queene,</hi> for the ſpace of thirty yeares extreame and reſtleſſe perſecution, no capitall lawes were made or executed. And in the<note n="c" place="margin">The booke intituled exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; not for religion, made by the late L. Burleigh.</note> booke intituled <hi>Execution for treaſon, and not for Religion,</hi> compoſed &amp; ſet forth by the late L. <hi>Burleigh</hi> then high Treaſourer of <hi>England,</hi> on whome for his great wiſdome and polecie, the menaging of the Common wealth of this Realme (vnder the <hi>Queene</hi> principally depended) <hi>Anno</hi> 1583. and <hi>Anno Regni Eliz.</hi> 26. it is in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe wordes ſet downe what fauour theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> found, in tearmes as followeth. <hi>And though there are many ſubiects knowne in the Realme that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer in ſome opinions of Religion from the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and yet doe alſo not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to profeſſe the ſame; yet in that they doe all profeſſe loyalty &amp; obedience to her</hi> Majeſtie, <hi>and offer readely in her defence to impugne and reſiſt any forraigne force, though it ſhould come or be procured from the</hi> Pope <hi>himſelfe,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">None of Q Maries Prieſts or Prelats per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> 
                  <hi>none of theſe ſort are for their contrary opinions in Religion perſecuted, or charged with any crimes or paines of treaſon, nor yet willingly ſearched in their conſciences for their contrary opinions that ſauour not of treaſon.</hi> After which Narration, he reckoneth vp great numbers, as<note n="e" place="margin">D. Heath, Arch-biſhop of Yorke.</note> 
                  <hi>D. Heath, Arch-biſhoppe</hi> of <hi>Yorke, B. Poole. B. Tunſtall, B. White, B. Oglethrop, B. Thurlby, B. Watſon, B. Turberuill: none of all theſe were preſſed with any capitall paine, though they maintayned the</hi> Popes <hi>authority,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21675:18"/>
againſt the lawes of the Realme:</hi> he recounteth<note n="a" place="margin">Abbot Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note> one <hi>Abbot</hi> &amp; diuers <hi>Deanes,</hi> whome he commendeth for learning, modeſtie &amp; knowledge, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth that none<note n="b" place="margin">None of all theſe held or puniſhed as trai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors, though they maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Popes authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lavves of the Realme.</note> of theſe, nor yet diuers others of the like morall, and indifferent carriage, were euer called to any capitall, or bloudie queſtion vpon matter of Religion; nor were not depriued of any of their goodes, or proper liuelihoods: of the like indulgence and leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty mention is made in the ſame booke, vſed towardes the layetie in wonderful pleaſing wordes as followeth.</p>
               <p>There are great numbers of others being lay men and of good poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſesſions in Lands, and men of credit in their countries, that doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their eſtates, though they holde contrarie opinions in Religion for the <hi>Popes</hi> authority, and yet none of them haue beene ſought he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto to be impeached in any point or quarrell of treaſon, or loſſe of life, member, or inheritaunce: <q rend="margQuotes">So that it may plainely appeare, it is not, nor hath not beene for contrary opinions in Religion; or for the <hi>Popes</hi> authority alone (as the Aduerſaries doe boldly and falſely publiſh) that euery perſon hath ſuffered death ſince her <hi>Maiesties</hi> Raigne: yet ſome of this ſorte are well knowne to hold opinion, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ought by authority of Gods word, to bee ſupreame and only head of the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church throughout the whole world, and that the <hi>Queenes Maiestie</hi> ought not to be<note n="c" place="margin">To deny the Q. to bee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe ouer Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vvith charge of trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.</note> gouerneſſe ouer any her ſubjectes in her Realmes, being perſons Eccleſiaſticall: yet for none of theſe points hath any perſon beene perſecuted with the charge of treaſon or in daunger of life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If then this were the caſe of <hi>Queene Maries Prieſts,</hi> and other quiet and faithfull ſubjectes in the late <hi>Queenes</hi> dayes, wee hope that our <hi>Prieſts</hi> (being aſwell qualified in al reſpectes to our Princes good liking &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as they were; both for quiet behauiour, ciuill life, and ſincere affection to your <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſeruice) may for our comfort obtayne aſmuch grace nowe, as they did then, without any ſuch aſſurance as our <hi>Priestes</hi> ſhall put in. And to make the caſe yet more cleare, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable; wee adde further, that ſince<note n="d" place="margin">No religion can conſiſt vvithout Prieſtes and Paſtors.</note> no Religion euer did or could conſiſt without <hi>Priestes, Pastors,</hi> and men to whome the diſpoſition of diuine miſteries did belong, we hope that our deſire to haue the benefitte of ſuch Clergie men, as may ſtand with the ſafty of our Prince and Country, is conformable to reaſon, as commaunded by the rules of conſcience, charity, and <hi>Christianity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that it may be more apparent to the world, that this our lowely <hi>Christian</hi> deſire, and humble demaund, ſhall not any wayes be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to your <hi>Maiesties</hi> Royall perſon or eſtate, we offer to anſwere
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21675:18"/>
perſon for perſon, and life for life, for euery ſuch <hi>Prieſt</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes offer for their Prieſtes.</note> as we ſhall make election of, and be permitted to haue in our ſeuerall howſes, for their fidelitie to your <hi>Maieſty</hi> and to the ſtate; by which meanes your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may be aſſured both of our number, and carriage of all ſuch <hi>Prieſts</hi> as ſhall remayne within the Realme, for whome (it is not credible) that we would ſo deeply ingage our ſelues without full knowledge of their diſpoſitions: their being here by this meanes ſhall be publike, the places of their abode certayne, their conuerſation and carriage ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the eyes of the Biſhoppes, Miniſters, and Iuſtices of peace in euery prouince and place where they ſhall liue: by which occaſion, there may probably ariſe a kinde of vertuous, and not altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable emulation betweene our <hi>Prieſts</hi> and your <hi>Ministers,</hi> who ſhall exceede and excell the other in vertuous liuing, and exemplarity of life, and other actes and exerciſes of pietie and deuotion, which muſt needes turne to the edification of the people, and extirpation of vice; and we ſhall be ſo much the more circumſpect and carefull of the comportmentes of our ſaid <hi>Priests,</hi> as our eſtate and ſecurity doth more directly depend vpon their honeſties and fidelities.</p>
               <p>To conclude, we doe and euer will (REDOVTED PRINCE) acknowledge your <hi>Maiesty</hi> our lawefull <hi>King</hi> and Soueraigne Lord, and will<note n="b" place="margin">Catholikes oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders.</note> defend and maintayne your <hi>Maieſties</hi> Heires and your Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors poſſeſſion, right, and Title, with life and liuelihood againſt all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendantes to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Further more, we will<note n="c" place="margin">Their profer to reueale and vvithſtand all treaſonable at temptes.</note> reueale, and to our powers withſtand and preuent any conſpiracy, or intended treaſon againſt the perſon of your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> your Heires and Succeſſors, and we will to our power defend your Realmes and Dominions againſt all inuaſions, or forraigne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, vpon what pretence ſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Wee doe, and will acknowledge due vnto your <hi>Maieſty</hi> from vs, what ſoeuer is due for a ſubject vnto his Prince and Soueraigne, either by the lawe of nature, or by the word of God, or hath beene vſed by any <hi>Catholike</hi> ſubject towardes your Highnes <hi>Catholike</hi> Progenitors; and this we will performe by proteſtation,<note n="d" place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes oath, and proteſtation.</note> oath, or in ſuch other manner, as ſhall ſeeme beſt to your <hi>Maieſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this ſame oath and proteſtation, our <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſo permitted, ſhall take before they ſhall be admitted into our howſes, otherwiſe they ſhall not haue releife of vs.</p>
               <p>In this ſorte (we doubte not) but that your <hi>Maiesty</hi> may both in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſecurity, take protection of our perſons, mittigate our former afflictions, and be aſſured of our future loyalties, loues, and affections, if
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21675:19"/>
you but pleaſe to take the viewe (which your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> may doe in this our <hi>Apologie</hi>) of the rules of our Doctrine and Religion, in thoſe caſes of the experience of our former actions, and of the abſolute complete forme of this our ſubmiſſion and allegeaunce: which bandes as they are moſt voluntary on our partes, ſo are they farre<note n="a" place="margin">Voluntary ſubmiſſion far to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before counterfeit conformity.</note> more honourable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and durable for your Highnes ſecuritie, then all the lawes and rigours in the world.</p>
               <p>And to ſay the truth, what greater glory or triumph can ſo magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimious a <hi>Monarch</hi> as your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> is, haue in this world, then to ſee and behold ſo many thouſandes of your faithfull Cittizens and ſubjectes, manumitted from ſeruitude, refuſcitated (as it were) from their ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, recalled from baniſhment, deliuered from priſons, rendred to their wiues and children, and reſtored to their priſtine honours, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reputations, by your <hi>Maieſties</hi> onely peereles Clemency and beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity; and to march before your triumphall chariot, with all inſignes of liberty, loue, freedome, joy, and eſtimation? of whoſe affections your <hi>Maieſty</hi> can be no leſſe aſſured, then a mercifull <hi>Father</hi> of dutifull children. <hi>Quos genuit in viſceribus charitatis &amp; pretatis ſuae:</hi> whome he hath begotten in the bowels of his charitie and pietie.</p>
               <p>And if that renowned <hi>Roman</hi> was wont to ſay, that he had rather<note n="b" place="margin">More glory in ſauing one Cittizen then in vanquiſhing a camp of eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> ſaue the life of one Cittizen, then ouercome a whole camp of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, what nowe ſhall your <hi>Maieſty</hi> gayne in giuing life and liberty to ſo many thouſandes (who are ſicke of the late <hi>Queenes</hi> euill) whome no phiſicke can cure, but the ſacred handes of our anoynted <hi>King,</hi> and are like to the<note n="c" place="margin">Cicero the pretor and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of Sicily</note> 
                  <hi>Sicilians,</hi> whome none but <hi>Cicero</hi> or the<note n="d" place="margin">Flaminius re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtored the Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians to their auncient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> 
                  <hi>Grecians,</hi> whome none but <hi>Flammius</hi> could deliuer from the heauy yoke, &amp; inſupportable ſeruitude, which the Pretors and Princes their predeceſſors had impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon them.</p>
               <p>We are but halfe men, if men at all, whome in theſe later dayes and times no man durſt defend, countenance, conuerſe with, or imploy, and (as your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath well ſaied) we are in deede but halfe ſubjects, not that our bodies, mindes, willes, wittes, vnderſtandinges, ſences, memories, judgementes, intentions; or our breathes, bloudes, or liues are deuided, or deuouted to the ſupreame honour or ſeruice of any terrene creature, other then your <hi>Maieſty</hi> only; but that the<note n="e" place="margin">In vvhat ſenſe the Catholikes may be called halfe ſubiectes</note> better halfe of our liuinges, goodes, friendes, and fortunes, wherewith we ſhould be the better able, and haue greater courage to ſerue your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> are taken from vs, and yet your <hi>Maieſties</hi> coffers little the better therefore.</p>
               <p>Our deſire then is (moſt gratious Prince) to become your <hi>Maiesties</hi> whole ſubjectes, and your <hi>Maieſty</hi> may ſo make vs in the twinckling of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21675:19"/>
your eye, or ſtampe of your foote, wherewith you are able to raiſe vp more armies, then euer <hi>Pompey</hi> the great could doe (from whom the metaphor is borrowed) in all his pompe and preſumtious pride.</p>
               <p>Vouchſafe then (DREAD SOVERAIGNE) to make vs as other your ſubjectes are of all profeſſions, intire and abſolute <hi>Engliſh-men;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vvith an Apoſtrophe to his Maieſtie.</note> for nothing (by Gods holy aſſiſtance) can or euer ſhall deuide vs from our ſubjection and dutifull affection to your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> but death which is <hi>vltima linea rerum,</hi> the laſt period of all thinges: for all other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions wee renounce, from all other ſeruices we diſclaime, but that only which is due to God in the ſupernaturall courſe of our ſaluation, which being gouerned by ſecret influences, and ſupernaturall concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of his grace, we alotte to God without diparagement to your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> aſſuring our ſelues that your <hi>Maieſty</hi> (ſo conuerſant in all good writers, and perfect Theologie) is well aſſured, that there is no diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo honourable for a Prince, as that which was attributed long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and nowe is not improperly applied to your <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Iupiter in coelis Caeſar regit omnia terris</l>
                  <l>Diuiſum imperum cum Ioue Caeſar habet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Whiles this <hi>Apologie</hi> or <hi>Petition</hi> was a printing, there came to my hands the copie of a letter written by the late baniſhed <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to the Lordes of his <hi>Maieſties</hi> moſt honourable priuie Councell, which for the cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the argument, I thought good to annexe hereunto.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21675:20"/>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21675:20"/>
            <head>THE COPPIE OF THE BANISHED PRIESTES LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER, <hi>TO THE LORDES OF HIS</hi> MAIESTIES MOST HONOVRABLE <hi>priuy Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE OVR <hi>VERY GOOD LORDES, THE LORDES</hi> OF HIS MAIESTIES MOST HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuy Councell.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOVRABLE.</hi> As we haue ſuffered for Chriſt his ſake, and the profeſsion of the true <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> religion, (which he planted with his pretious bloud) many yeares impriſonment, and depriuation of all worldly comfortes and commodities: ſo doe we with the like patience and humilitie endure this hard and heauy ſentence of exile, which is a certaine kinde of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill death, or rather a languiſhing and continuall dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, especially to them that haue the honour and ſafety of their Prince and Country, in that recommendation, as we euer both haue had, and haue. Notwithſtanding leaſt it might be imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to vs hereafter, that this baniſhment was rather an extraordinary fauour and grace, then an vndeſerued puniſhment or penalty: we thought it our dutie to let your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours vnderſtand, that as we are content with patience and humility to ſuffer, and ſupport whatſoeuer you ſhould impoſe vpon vs for our Religion: ſo are we bound with all, to make proteſtation af our innocencie, according to that of S. <hi>Peter: Nemo veſtrum patiatur vt fur, aut latro, aut maledicus, aut alienorum appetitor: ſi autem vt Chriſtianus, non erubeſcat, glorificet autem Deum in iſto nomine.</hi> May it pleaſe your Lordſhips therefore to vnderſtand, that the quality and condition of thoſe that are comprehended vnder the ſelfe ſame ſentence of baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is very different and conſiderable, both in honour and conſcience: among the which ſome there are that came voluntarily into priſon, vpon a proclamation ſet out by your Lordſhips in the late <hi>Queenes</hi> dayes and name, with aſſurance of fauour vpon ſuch their ſubmiſſion: ſome came neither voluntarily into the priſon, nor into the Realme, &amp; therefore not ſubiect to any cenſure: &amp; all of them haue beene euer moſt faithfull
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21675:21"/>
ſeruantes and affectionate well-willers of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and haue to ſhewe vnder the great zeale of <hi>England</hi> his <hi>Majeſties</hi> gratious generall pardon, by which they are reſtored vnto the peace of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and place of true ſubiectes: ſince which time they haue committed nothing againſt his <hi>Majeſties</hi> quiet Crowne and dignity; as being euer ſince in captiuitie: and therefore in the rigour and extreamities of thoſe lawes (which in their beſt ſence and nature were euer held, both extreame and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous) cannot be puniſhed by any forme or courſe of lawe, with ſo ſeuere a correction, as <hi>aqua &amp; igne interdici,</hi> to be depriued of the benefit of the common Ayre and Elementes of our moſt naturall and deare Country. Yet ſithence it is your Lordſhippes pleaſure we ſhould be tranſported, we are content (in ſigne of obedience and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to that we ſee is your order) for this time to forbeare the Realme for a while, and to abſent ourſelues; reputing our ſelues notwithſtanding, as men free from all danger or penalty of lawes; and neither by this fact of baniſhment, nor by any other act of our neceſſary retourne into our Country hereafter in worſe eſtate, then your Lordſhips found vs in the priſon, when your Lordſhippes warrant came for the carrying vs out of the Realme. And ſo hoping your honours will conceiue of vs, as of men that haue the feare &amp; grace of God before our eyes, and the ſincere loue of our Prince &amp; Country in our hartes, and dutifull reuerence and reſpect to your Lordſhippes in all actions: we humbly beſeech your honours, that if we happen for want of health, or other helpes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our reliefe, to retourne hereafter into the Realme, this baniſhment may not any way aggrauate our caſe, or make vs leſſe capable of fauour and grace, then we were the <hi>xxj.</hi> of <hi>September</hi> when your Lordſhippes order came to remoue vs from post to piller, from priſon to exile: &amp; ſo deſiring God to inſpire your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes (vpon whoſe reſolutions dependes the repoſe of the Realme, and the ſaluation or perdition of many thouſand ſoules) with his holy grace and aſſiſtance in all your moſt graue and waightie determinations, in moſt humble and dutifull manner we take our leaue, from the Sea ſide this <hi>24.</hi> of <hi>SEPTEMBER. 1604.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>His Majeſties true and loyall ſubjectes, and your honours moſt humble ſeruantes, <hi>The late baniſhed Prieſtes.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
